Guide to the Native American Educational Services Sol Tax Papers 1908-1993
University of Chicago Library
Native American Educational Services. Tax, Sol. Papers
1908-1993
24 linear feet (43 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Sol Tax (1907-1996) was a prominent cultural anthropologist at the University of Chicago who was instrumental to the foundation of the Native American Educational Services (NAES) as an offshoot of his work with Native Americans in Chicago and throughout the Americas. This collection consists of 24 linear feet of materials related to Tax's research on American Indians, especially those in and around Chicago, as well as his work with various social issues including race and poverty. The bulk of this collection is made up of publications and papers collected for research, as well as newsletters and newspapers written by or about American Indians. The rest of the collection contains correspondence and administrative materials from organizations with which Dr. Tax was involved.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Sol Tax (1907-1996) was a prominent cultural anthropologist. He completed a Bachelor's degree at the University of Wisconsin in Madison in 1931, a M.A. and Ph.D. at the University of Chicago (1932 and 1935). He took a faculty position at University of Chicago in 1940 and remained there until 1977. Tax founded the academic journal Current Anthropology (1959), served on the National Research Council Committee on Latin American Anthropology (1946-1954), served on the President's Task Force on Indian Affairs (1965-1969), was Director of the Smithsonian Institute's Center for the Study of Man (1969-1977), served as President of the American Anthropological Association (1958-1959) and edited that Association's Journal, American Anthropologist (1953-1956). He was a pioneer in the field of action anthropology, published many academic articles and corresponded with researchers and activists.
Tax was an active organizer of the 1961 American Indian Chicago Conference (AICC, also called the American Indian Charter Convention or Conference), which produced the path-breaking Declaration of Indian Purpose, and worked to coordinate pan-tribal research on education. Tax was instrumental in the creation of the Native American Educational Services (NAES) in 1970 as an offshoot of earlier organizing efforts by Chicago Indians and their supporters.
Scope Note
This collection consists of Sol Tax's papers from his work for Native American Educational Services. The collection has been arranged into fourteen short series. All series have been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
Series I: American Indian Center, is composed mostly of board minutes for 1978-1980, as well as several reports and brochures in regards to the American Indian Center. Further references to this center are scattered through Tax's correspondence and papers in the American Indians and Chicago Indians series.
Series II: American Indian Chicago Conference 1961 (AICC), includes photocopies of drafts of the Declaration of Purpose, the originals of which are kept in the Smithsonian Archives.
Series III: American Indians, contains the bulk of Dr. Tax's Indian work, which contains mainly drafts and papers by students and colleagues. Dr. Tax evidently kept this material for reference in his own research and teaching. The series contains one folder on the National Indian Youth Council, which contains drafts of an undated proposal. Dr. Tax's own publications are found in this series, as well as in the Anthropology series. Some folders have been removed and filed separately in the Oversized Series due to their large size.
Series IV: Anthropology, contains material covering the span of Dr. Tax's career, with the bulk falling in the 1970s. The series contains mostly papers and drafts of other scholars, but it includes three folders of Dr. Tax's publications, including some drafts.
Series V: Carnegie Cross-Cultural Education Project, CCCE, contains several folders that include articles and other materials related to education, mostly from the 1960s, as well as reports from the project itself.
Series VI: Chicago Indians, contains copies of Dr. Tax's CAICOC plans, as well as correspondence dealing with Indian relocation in the 1950s and 1960s.
Series VII: Finding Aids, is comprised of two folders that contain acquisition lists, notes accompanying donations, and copies of Smithsonian and University of Chicago finding aids to Tax collections.
Series VIII: Fox Project, includes a documentary history of the project and some related letters and reports. The administrative folder contains financial records from the University of Chicago, including scholarship fund roles. The photographic plates of the documentary history of the Fox Project have been separated and moved to the Oversized series due to their size.
Series IX: Latin American, represents mostly Dr. Tax's early work in Mexico and Guatemala. However, later materials have been mixed into the folders, reflecting Dr. Tax's lifelong interest in Native peoples south of the United States.
Series X: Native American Educational Services, NAES, represents bits of administrative materials that Dr. Tax acquired concerning planning and operation of NAES. His files on the Community Board Training Project are also found here.
Series XI: Newberry Library, contains several folders made up almost entirely of published materials acquired by Dr. Tax.
Series XII: Newsletters/Newspapers, includes copies of newsletters and newspapers from the 1960s and 1970s published by or related to Native American affairs in North and South America.
Series XIII: Social Issues, represents Dr. Tax's interest and research in social issues other than American Indians, primarily education, urban poverty, and racism. It is divided into four subseries: Community Development, Education, Poverty, and Race and Ethnicity.
Series XIV: Oversized, contains material removed from other series and filed separately due to their size. It contains several maps and the negative plates of the Fox Project documentary history.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
Tax, Sol. Papers
Subject Headings
Tax, Sol, 1907-; NAES College; Indian universities and colleges -- United States; Indians of North America; Indians of North America -- Education (Higher)
INVENTORY
- Series I: American Indian Center
  Series I contains materials dealing with the administrative records of the American Indian Center, mostly the minutes of meetings of the Board of Directors. It also includes several brochures for events hosted by the American Indian center and service reports. References to the American Indian Center is scattered throughout the remainder of the collection. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Brochures for American Indian Center and events, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Director's Report to the Board of Directors, minutes, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Director's Report to the Board of Directors, minutes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Director's Report to the Board of Directors, minutes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Semi-annual and annual service reports to the American Indian Center, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: American Indian Chicago Conference
  Series II contains primarily materials dealing with invitations and lists of guests and presenters for the American Indian Chicago Conference. It also includes photocopies of the Declaration of Purpose.
  - Address labels and cards, no date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mailing packets and progress reports on conference, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series III: American Indians
  Series III contains publications from many different sources on American Indian issues. This series also contains the majority of Dr. Tax's work, as well as drafts and papers by students and colleagues. There are also several project proposals and brochures for American Indian meetings contained in this series, as well as correspondence between Dr. Tax and other researchers. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Bibliographies on North American Indians, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brochures for American Indian groups and materials, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brochures for American Indian groups and materials, 1964-1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Brochures for American Indian groups and materials, 1978-1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cherokee Project, materials on Cherokee language, article reprints, article draft, surveys, 1962-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clippings from newspapers and articles on American Indian issues, 1908-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Century of Dishonor," H.H. Jackson, article reprints, correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, William Brophy, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, incoming, 1982-1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Indian Education, brochures, government reports, 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Indian Education, brochures, government reports, 1966-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Kinzua Dam Project, article reprints, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Meetings, minutes, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Menominee Termination Act, correspondence, government memos, 1954-1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, correspondence, newsletters, drafts, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous newsletters, 1957-1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous newsletters, 1980-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Papers and drafts, Ba-Cl, 1951-1975 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Papers and drafts, Co-Fo, 1945-1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Papers and drafts, Ge-Kr, 1952-1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Papers and drafts, Le-Lu, 1962-1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Papers and drafts, Ma-Nu, 1951-1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Papers and drafts, Pa-Sk, 1949-1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Papers and drafts, Sn-Wa, 1954-1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Papers and drafts, Wah-Wax, 1964-1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Papers and drafts, We-Wo, 1961-1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - President's Task Force, correspondence, travel documents, 1966-1971 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Proposals and project reports, 1953-1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Reports and journal articles, 1956-1974 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Seven Nations, draft and article reprint, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Sol Tax's publications, 1954-1964 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Sol Tax's publications, 1964-1971 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Turtle Island, draft, chapters 1-2, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Turtle Island, draft, chapters 3-4, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Turtle Island, draft, chapters 5-7, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Turtle Island, draft, chapters 8-9, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - United States Government papers on American Indian policies, 1954-1967 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Urban Indians, drafts and surveys, 1959-1976 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Workshop on Indian Affairs, correspondence, program, 1956-1969 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Alphabetized publications, A, 1949-1984 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Alphabetized publications, Ba-Be, 1959-1967 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Alphabetized publications, Bl-Bu, 1952-1982 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Alphabetized publications, C, 1950-1967 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Alphabetized publications, D, 1935-1972 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Alphabetized publications, E, 1937-1970 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Alphabetized publications, F, 1951-1983 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Alphabetized publications, G, 1945-1970 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Alphabetized publications, Ha-He, 1942-1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Alphabetized publications, He-Ho, 1959-1975 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Alphabetized publications, Ho-Hu, 1953-1969 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Alphabetized publications, J, 1964-1975 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Alphabetized publications, K, 1948-1974 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Alphabetized publications, La-Lee, 1940-1960 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Alphabetized publications, Lei-Lu, 1928-1979 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Alphabetized publications, M, 1932-1972 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Alphabetized publications, N, 1954-1960 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Alphabetized publications, O, 1933-1980 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Alphabetized publications, P, 1950-1975 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Alphabetized publications, P-Q, 1940-1983 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Alphabetized publications, R, 1915-1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Alphabetized publications, Sa, 1923-1950 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Alphabetized publications, Sc-Sh, 1920-1977 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Alphabetized publications, Si-Sm, 1949-1978 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Alphabetized publications, So-Sp, 1941-1960 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Alphabetized publications, St-Sz, 1951-1974 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Alphabetized publications, T, 1957-1973 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Alphabetized publications, U-Wa, 1949-1962 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Alphabetized publications, Wa-Wi, 1916-1973 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous publications, A, 1958-1978 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous publications, B, 1962-1981 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous publications, C, 1963-1978 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous publications, D-E, 1957-1968 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous publications, E-J, 1968-1976 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous publications, K-R, 1962-1971 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous publications, S-Z, 1953-1984 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Journal publications, Indians on Federal Reservations in the United States: A Digest, Portland Area, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Journal publications, Indians on Federal Reservations in the United States: A Digest, Billings Area, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Journal publications, Indians on Federal Reservations in the United States: A Digest, Aberdeen Area, 1959 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Journal publications, Indians on Federal Reservations in the United States: A Digest, Albuquerque Area, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Journal publications, Indians on Federal Reservations in the United States: A Digest, Oklahoma City Area and Florida, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Journal publications, Indians on Federal Reservations in the United States: A Digest, Phoenix Area, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Anthropology
  Series IV contains manuscripts and publications on anthropological issues. It contains the bulk of the rest of Dr. Tax's work presented in this collection, but is broader in nature than the American Indians series. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Book reviews, 1946-1961 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Manuscripts, A, 1973-1976 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Manuscripts, B, 1943-1968 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Manuscripts, C-Fa, 1954-1973 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Manuscripts, Fr, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts, G-L, 1956-1986 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts, M-P, 1966-1973 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts, R-T, 1953-1985 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Manuscripts, U-W, 1947-1975 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous publications, newsletters, drafts, papers, 1958-1971 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters and brochures, 1968-1985 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters and brochures, 1985-1993 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Numbered manuscripts and publications, A-Ce, 1966-1985 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Numbered manuscripts and publications, Ci-Fa, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Numbered manuscripts and publications, G-Ho, 1970-1977 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Numbered manuscripts and publications, H-Mc, 1970-1985 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Numbered manuscripts and publications, Me-Ni, 1971-1979 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Numbered manuscripts and publications, P-Wa, 1969-1978 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Numbered manuscripts and publications, Wi, 1970-1979 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Reprinted and photocopied articles, 1948-1988 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Student papers and drafts, A-Bri, 1971-1991 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Student papers and drafts, Bro-La, 1988-1992 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Student papers and drafts, Lo-St, 1986-1992 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Tax publications, 1937-1949 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Tax publications, 1950-1958 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Tax publications, 1960-1988 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Tax publications, 1968-1988 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences newsletters, 1970-1993 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, A, 1952 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, An-B, 1964-1968 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, C-Co, 1960-1975 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, Cu, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, Cu-Id, 1957-1993 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, In-Mi, 1950-1974 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, Mi-No, 1968-1977 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, No-Pr, 1960-1993 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, Pr-Sk, 1958-1975 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, So-Te, 1964-1992 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous social sciences publications, Th-Z, 1951-1967 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Weilgart, Dr. John, correspondence, surveys, draft, aUI – The Language of Space, 1962-1969 (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Series V: Carnegie Cross-Cultural Education Project (CCCE)
  Series V contains materials related to education in general and the Carnegie Cross-Cultural Education Project specifically. This includes correspondence with scholars and progress reports prepared by the Project. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, newsletters, 1956-1971 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper article photocopies, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Progress reports, 1963-1967 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Report drafts from Carnegie Cross-Cultural Education Project, 1962-1967 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Wahrhaftig papers, drafts of articles, 1965 (Box 23, Folder 1)
- Series VI: Chicago Indians
  Series VI contains materials related specifically to Chicago Indians. This includes population distribution maps, directories of Indians in the area, brochures for local events, and newsletters written by local Native Americans. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Directories of American Indians, 1976-1985 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Event brochures and invitations, 1965-1989 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Indian Voices, newsletters, 1962-1964 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Indian Voices, newsletters, 1965 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Indian Voices, newsletters, 1966-1968 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Sol Tax's maps and census papers, American Indians, 1950-1960 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Sol Tax's maps and census papers, American Indians, 1950-1961 (Box 24, Folder 2)
- Series VII: Finding Aids
  Series VII contains two folders that contain acquisition lists, notes accompanying donations, and copies of Smithsonian and University of Chicago finding aids to Tax collections. It has been arranged chronologically.
  - Finding aids, bibliographies, correspondence, 1968-1981 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Finding aids, bibliographies, correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 24, Folder 4)
- Series VIII: Fox Project
  Series VIII contains articles, drafts, and correspondence related to the Fox Project, a study of the culture of the Fox and Sauk Indians. There are also drafts of papers and symposium papers. There is a copy of a documentary history of the Fox Project in this series, but the negative plates of this documentary have been relocated to the Oversized series due to their large size. This series has been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Administrative materials, expense records, correspondence, schedules, 1948-1962 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Documentary history of the Fox Project, bound, 1955 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Gearing, Fred, draft of report, 1955 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Mesquakie Tribe, article reprints, summary reports, drafts, correspondence, 1955-1969 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Peattie, Lisa, article drafts, no date (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Proposals and correspondence, 1954-1962 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Symposium presentations and schedule, 1955 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Paper drafts, "Values in Action – The Fox Project," Sol Tax, 1957-1958 (Box 25, Folder 8)
- Series IX: Latin America
  Series IX contains materials related to Dr. Tax's interests in Mexico and Guatemala, as well as Central American Indians in general. This includes mainly article publications and newsletters about Central American Indians. There is also a great deal of correspondence about political and social issues in Central America related to Native Americans. This series has been organized alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Article and manuscript drafts, correspondence, 1950-1982 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Central American social issues, articles, newsletters, correspondence regarding political and social situations in Central America, 1971-1988 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - CLASicos Newsletter, numbers 19-23, 1986-1987 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Guatemala – News in Brief, newsletters, numbers 1-15, 17-23, 1986-1988 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous publications, newsletters, directories, A-I, 1947-1988 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous publications, newsletters, directories, I-S, 1955-1992 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Partners, newspapers, 1976-1989 (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Series X: Native American Educational Services (NAES)
  Series X contains primarily administrative materials related to the Native American Educational Services, mostly in its planning and operation. There is a great deal of material related to the Community Board Training Project, mostly proposals for funding or grants from various organizations. This series has been organized alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Alumni meetings, correspondence, conference summaries, 1985 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Bilingual Teacher Training Project, announcement of job opening, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Bylaws and Committees, minutes, drafts of report, 1979-1982 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - CBTP, Community Board Training Project, Information and Assistance Center proposal, 1987 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - CBTP, Community Board Training Project, evaluative summary, drafts, March 7, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - CBTP, Community Board Training Project, proposal to Administration for Native Americans, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - CBTP, Community Board Training Project, proposal to Borg-Warner Foundation, 1983-1984 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - CBTP, Community Board Training Project, proposal to United Presbyterian Church, 1982-1983 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - CBTP, Community Board Training Project, seminar proceedings, "Executive Search and Selection," January 31, 1981 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - CBTP, Community Board Training Project, staff meetings, minutes, 1984 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Center for Community Research and Assistance, correspondence, memos, 1982 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - College catalogs and Commencement, 1981-1986 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence on social issues and articles, 1958-1983 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Funding reports from Avon Products, Inc., correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - General staff meeting, minutes, 1984 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - "How NAES Became a Corporation," article draft, correspondence, 1977 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - Job descriptions, and job opening announcements, 1985 (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - Menominee correspondence, student correspondence, 1989 (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Menominee site, personnel contracts, 1989 (Box 27, Folder 17)
  - News article copies and three-year plan draft, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 18)
  - "Student Study Guide," 1984 (Box 27, Folder 19)
  - Supply lists for Chicago site, 1984 (Box 27, Folder 20)
- Series XI: Newberry Library